What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we discover the some of the
health benefits of eating onions.
Onions are potentially a
good source of antioxidants,
though interestingly, the
antioxidants are concentrated
in the outer layers immediately
under the papery peel.
Unfortunately, most consumers
discard these most nutrient-rich
outermost layers, thus
losing a valuable part.
Here are some numbers.
Look at that!
More than 10 times
more antioxidants in the
outer layer of white onions,
compared to the core.
You’ll also note that
yellow onions in general
have more antioxidants than white.
And red onions beat
them both, based on three
different antioxidant testing methods.
That’s why I always try to buy red.
Though red onions are
indeed slightly better, yellow
or white onions are no
slouches, containing
considerable levels of
antioxidant activity.
So, nutritious, sure, but
are there any particular
clinical benefits to onion consumption?
Evidently, older white women
who consumed onions at least
once a day had an overall bone
density that was 5% greater than
individuals who consumed onions
no more than once a month (P < 0.03).
Now 5% might not sound like
a lot, but that improvement in
bone density could potentially
translate into decreasing
their risk of hip fracture
by more than 20%
if indeed, it was cause and effect.
Daily administration of onion did
cause a big bump in bone density.
This opens the possibility for
a low-cost, safe, and effective
nutritional approach
to osteoporosis and—
you guessed it...in the rat.
Another rodent study.
Rats!
But finally, here we go.
Tremendous strides have been made
in treating osteoporosis with
drugs, but they have the potential
for serious adverse side effects,
so scientists have drawn
their attention to natural remedies.
So, let’s randomize people
to drink... onion juice
or placebo onion juice.
I don’t know what sounds worse:
sugary onion juice
or fake sugary onion juice.
And as if drinking onion
juice wasn’t bad enough,
it was all for nothing.
It didn’t even work.
What about the antiallergy
activities of shallots
and any therapeutic effects
on helping allergic runny noses?
Sixteen such patients were
randomized equally into
an antihistamine group or a
group that got antihistamines
plus some capsules containing
dried shallot powder.
And it looked like the
shallot group did better,
but there was actually no
statistically significant difference
in total symptoms
between the two groups;
so, another #OnionFail.
There has to be something
onions can do.
What about testing the effects of
fresh yellow onion consumption
on breast cancer patients to try
to decrease the toxic effects
of a chemotherapy drug
called doxorubicin?
Unfortunately, no significant
benefit was found on decreasing
damage to the liver or heart.
But here we go . . . finally,
a clinical benefit to onions.
The consumption of fresh
yellow onion ameliorates
the high blood sugars and
insulin resistance in breast cancer
patients during doxorubicin-
based chemotherapy.
Doxorubicin isn’t just toxic
to the liver and heart,
but it may also contribute
to insulin resistance.
So, let’s do a randomized, triple-blind,
controlled clinical trial
randomizing patients to
like a whole onion a day
or a third of an onion
a day. What happened?
The high onion group experienced
a significant decrease
in blood sugars and insulin resistance
compared to the low onion group.
They went up in the low onion group
but down in the high onion group.
So, make onions your friend.
What’s the worst that can happen—
a little onion breath and BO?
Probably the least of your worries
if you have cancer on chemotherapy.
In our next story,
we learn what an eighth of a
teaspoon a day of onion powder
can do for body fat,
and what can raw red
onion do for cholesterol.
Enter "The Effect of Steamed Onion
Consumption on Body Fat
in Overweight Subjects."
The researchers used steamed onions
so they could better disguise it
against placebo, and dried it into
an onion powder, and gave people
just a minuscule amount, about
an eighth of a teaspoon a day.
Surely, a little daily dusting of onion
powder isn't going to affect the course
of people's weight, but check out
these results reported in the abstract:
a significant reduction in body fat
mass on both DEXA scan
and measured by CT scan —
a significant decrease in the areas
of whole fat, visceral fat,
and subcutaneous fat.
Hold on. If a little onion powder
is so effective for weight loss,
why wasn't it featured in my
book "How Not to Diet?"
Because, as so often happens
in studies, the spin in the abstract
doesn't accurately represent
the actual data.
Here are the DEXA scan results.
No significant change of fat in the
group that got the placebo capsules;
they only appeared to lose
about a spoonful of fat.
Whereas the group unknowingly taking
an eighth of a teaspoon of onion powder
stuffed into capsules lost nearly
one and a half pounds of body fat,
a significant drop from baseline,
but not a statistically significant drop
compared to the placebo group,
meaning the loss could very
well have been due to chance.
Same thing with the CT scan results:
five times more loss of overall fat,
and 30 times more loss of
the dangerous visceral fat,
but did not reach statistical
significance compared to placebo.
A more recent study tried four
teaspoons of onion powder a day
and similarly failed to
accelerate the loss of body fat
compared to placebo,
but the placebo was also
four teaspoons of
onion powder a day.
They used yellow onions versus white
onions, and it seems they both may
have caused a loss of body fat, without
a significant difference between them.
Either way, you can look at these
two studies and say, yeah,
but what are the downsides?
I mean just an eighth teaspoon of onion
powder a day. Why not give it a try?
Can't hurt, but we just
don't have confidence
that it's actually going to help.
Turning now to polycystic ovary syndrome,
also known as P.C.O.S., or PCOS.
It's one of the most common hormone
disorders, affecting 5% to 10%
of reproductive-aged women. In addition
to symptoms like irregular periods,
PCOS is also a pre-diabetic state
with decreased insulin sensitivity.
PCOS treatment is a big challenge
due to medication side effects.
So what about using dietary options?
How about a randomized controlled
clinical trial of raw red onion intake?
Why onions? Well, onion extracts
evidently help in diabetic rats,
and more importantly
in diabetic humans,
but evidently not in
non-diabetic humans.
PCOS sufferers are kind of pre-diabetic,
so would it work for them?
First, let's look at those
other two studies.
Here's the diabetic one on the "Metabolic
Effects of Onion and Green Beans."
Diabetics spent a week eating
either a small onion a day,
or the same diet with about five
cups of green beans instead,
and they both worked.
The onion group dropped people's
blood sugars by about 10%,
and the green beans more like 15%.
Here's the study that supposedly shows
no blood sugar benefits for non-diabetics.
It's true, onions don't lower normal
blood sugars, which is a good thing,
but check out what happens
when you feed people sugar.
Have people down about two tablespoons
of corn syrup, and their blood sugars
shoot up over the next two hours before
their body's able to tamp it back down.
But give people the exact same amount
of sugar, but with more and more onion,
and the blood sugar spike
is significantly dampened,
almost as much as if you had instead
given them an antidiabetic drug.
And we see the same when you
give people a shot of adrenaline —
with or without onions.
So, are there blood sugar benefits for
diabetics and non-diabetics alike?
No difference was found between
the higher and lower onion groups
of PCOS patients, nor
were there any differences
in a marker of inflammation
between the two groups.
But women with PCOS aren't
just at higher risk for diabetes
and inflammation,
but also high cholesterol.
Women with PCOS are
seven times more likely
to have a heart attack, the
number one killer of women,
but raw red onion consumption
appears to be effective
as a cholesterol-lowering food,
though the high onion group
only dropped their LDL cholesterol
about five points, not significantly
different than the low onion group.
I did find this study from nearly 50
years ago where researchers fed
people nearly an entire stick of
butter, and their cholesterol shot up
about 30 points within
hours of consumption,
but only nine points or three points
when combined with about a
third cup of raw or boiled onion,
the moral of the story being
don't eat a stick of butter.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.